<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<reviews itemIdentifier="TheVoynichManuscript">
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Thank you</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Nice</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>nanato</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2010-12-31 18:10:30</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2010-12-31 18:10:30</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I just saw the documentary and i really enjoyed it ,many thanks for the pdf you made a great job .</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Awesome work</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>temet.nosce</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2012-04-26 21:39:18</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2012-04-26 21:39:18</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>in my opinion  this manuscript may not  be  deciphered  for  many  reasons! one reason  may  be  that  people  may  be  placing  too  much  focus  on  the  text  itself...the  answer  to  the  manuscript  may  very  well  be  in  the  drawings  on  the  pages. also  Im  assuming  that  the  writing  or  the  text  may  also  be  something  like  that  of  the  green  language  used  by  Nostradamus  in  his  quartrains.I  have  also  noticed  the  use  of  an  "H"  like  symbol  in  the  text..that  may  just  be  a  "pointer"  so  to  speak  because  it  comes  up  so  many  times  in  the  manuscript.  In  closing,how  long  did  it  take  people  to  decipher  hyrogliphics? If  that  was  possible  then  so  is  decoding  the  VOnich  Manuscript&gt;&gt;</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>decipher</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>niamod</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2012-05-19 20:03:31</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2012-05-19 20:03:31</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>thank you! I would like to recommend Terence McKenna's talk on the Voynich Manuscript to anyone interested in it, simply amazing.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>outstanding</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>EROCx1</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2012-08-03 17:25:01</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2012-08-03 17:25:01</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>although the text itself is indicipherable, its evident by the illustrations that this book is describing certain plants either for medicinal purposes or for documentation purposes.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>medicinal</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>kenny wilson</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2012-10-24 02:36:26</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2012-10-24 02:36:26</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>The Voynich Manuscript is immediately interesting. I've seen some work in Italian anagrams but am not entirely convinced. I've made some translations of the plants into the Macedonian language. I believe the text is a prototype alphabet of Macedonian. My video series shows my work. It took 1,000 years for heiroglyphs to be translated because everybody kept making the same mistake. I don't believe in the alien dropping the book off for humanity theory. Aliens have a better way of communicating their thoughts.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Amazing.</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>AZstarwatcher</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2012-12-28 16:27:53</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2012-12-28 16:27:53</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>This is the first five books of King James. Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy. Even though this was wrote 200 years prior.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>decoded</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>cmccoy</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-01-05 06:42:56</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-01-05 06:42:56</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>This is undoubtedly an alchemical manuscript in the Paracelsus tradition of using alchemy to produce superior medicines. It may even have been written by him as the time period (around A D 1500) corresponds. Nearly all alchemical manuscripts of this period are undecipherable to the uninitiated. The traditional reason for this was to keep the information out of the hands of the unworthy, while at the same time giving useful information to those that had been initiated into the Mysteries. The time period of the creation of this MS also corresponds to the founding of the Rosicrucian Brotherhood. Saint Germain, who may have been a Rosicrucian, uses a similar script in his La Tres Trinosophie (The Divine Threefold Sophia), discovered by Manly Hall. For more on the language of the Mysteries see my SENSA: The Lost Language of the Ancient Mysteries. Dorje Jinpa</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Alchemical Manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Pentarba</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-01-21 01:17:25</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-01-21 01:17:25</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>That is the one and only real solution of the Voynich manuscript.

In english:
http://fastwalkers.de/downloads/thevoynichmanuscript.pdf

In german:
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KpJfaUdZC20

http://fastwalkers.de/downloads/dasvoynichmanuskript.pdf

Read and break with your worldview...</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>The solution</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Hyperborea</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-03-07 22:26:22</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-03-07 22:26:22</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>The algorithm is written on page 116. There is written the at Czech language. Have you found ( algorithm)!!!
......................................

VM is encrypted and written in Czech language. It is also used gematria. The manuscript describes the Czech history. The manuscript began Silesian piastovna Hlohovská Anna, wife of John II. of Rosenberg. The last entry made last Rosenberg Petr Vok.

 http://zlatodej.blog.cz/</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Voynich Manuscript ( Little to help and advice you)</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Zlatodej Prof.</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-04-21 18:06:37</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-04-21 17:58:15</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Zlatodej Prof</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>The Voynich Manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>rounes123</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-05-03 14:08:34</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-05-03 14:08:34</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>It is also interesting how so many people can look at the same thing, clam they have decoded it and it comes out totally different from what any others say they have decoded.

There are many ways to encode a message that are one-way encryption or totally unbreakable without the key, even with today's computer cryptoanalysis programs. 

Here is a very interesting site written by a professional cryptanalysis. 

http://www.ciphermysteries.com/the-voynich-manuscript</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Interesting from a historical point of view</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Kwai Noi</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-06-14 11:39:58</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-06-14 11:39:58</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>People think too hard about this.

It's probably a 5th generation copy of an Arabic (or Farsi or Greek or etc) herbarium made by a series of medieval scribes who had no idea what they were copying but tried their hardest to keep it as accurate as possible.

Any resemblance to the original text is probably long since lost and the pictures not far behind. (though the plant on page 6 has a pretty accurate water lily leaf and rhizome).

Anyway, it's good to see a nice hi res version available for free.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>People think too hard about this</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>WaldorfTBeagle</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-06-22 22:37:03</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-06-22 22:37:03</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Read the supposed expert's testimony.  "Pseudo religion", indeed.  He doubts the translation and scrutiny of tens of thousands of scholars for 3,000 years (Old Testament), says there were no "Hebrews" (it's a mistranslation as he states), or "Israel" (ditto) and therefor the entire world is on the wrong "track".  While to me this language does appear to be some form of Latin written without grammatical knowledge (not by scholars, at least not as we view them), for your hero to state that the entire Bible is invalid is hubris beyond belief.  I don't know what this manuscript is or is not.  I do know that, viewing it in its entirety, I was left with an uncomfortable "feeling".  I won't change my world view based upon one arrogant man's self aggrandized assumptions.  Why isn't he chairing a department at Yale, why isn't he world famous, if he's correct?  By their fruits ye shall know them.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Hyperborea - ?</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>MercyNeeded</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-06-23 14:51:04</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-06-23 14:51:04</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Really Interesting read..</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Voynich</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Al_Jo_</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-06-25 16:51:50</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-06-24 17:43:55</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>While reviewing the manuscript, it gives me the feeling that the writer is attempting to convey about the type of plants which were available in the vicinity. Each plant has been drawn with roots which the plant has, the type of leaves &amp; flowers it bears also fruits if present. Another observation: a zodiac has been drawn, probably to indicate the period when such plants were present in their surroundings.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>The Voynich Manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Ramesh037</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-06-25 06:33:14</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-06-25 06:33:14</createdate>
    <stars>2</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I believe if yo try to read the images rather than the text you get the "picture"  I believe it is showing the cycle,s of life ie the seasons, the cycles of eclipse,s of the sun.
The weather. A woman's cycle.
When I first looked at this I decided to look at the images
Rather than try to de cipher the text of which some appear 
To resemble the Russian alphabet .

Further to this review, if you look at the sketches of the buildings they look extraordinary like the Kremlin.
As to cycles of life take a look at the sketches of women, have the naughty ones been removed.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>voynich manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Jabberwoky1</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-09-09 21:31:54</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-06-25 20:37:25</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>The Book basically describes transpeicies  migration. How Fauna based life form migrate from plant to animal - e.i. human life forms. The Pictures are 28, 30 leaf, Red Green - red green transformations. Nickel - Zinc Lunar period cycles. Some pictures show the DNA chain. The women in the pictures represent the Borgship Mother earth. 

Other websites show 3d interpretation of the pictures, suggesting prior knowledge. Richard Prior Knowledge, John Richard prior knowledge - The flaming fag coke whore from hell. A.k.a Mother Earth. The Black hole star in the sky.

I give the book a low rating because it is just another example of this asshole lying to every living human in the world. We are one A &amp; E. Adam and Eve. Adam and Evil! Fu John! A.K.A. MOM</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Nickle People</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Minnesota Multiple Monodot</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-06-25 23:15:17</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-06-25 23:15:17</createdate>
    <stars>1</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>This in my opinion is not a language whatsoever its a code, although some of the symbols are familiar such as the Greek letter R,T,TH, and many more in lower case. Also the manuscript has nothing to do with plants its just a means of confusion. The mind has to be opened away from 21st century modern computerized motions then taken back to see the manuscripts future.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Language</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>tyguk</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-07-23 15:19:08</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-07-23 15:19:08</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>while i viewing this book i noticed the drawings and details of plants are in its physical looks and the surrounding text is supposed to be the information regarding the plant. zodiac signs and moon cycles are some how related to women cycles and discomfort. Some last pages are the formulation and potions and medications compositions made with the help of these herbs and plants for women related problems.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>suggested this is a herb formulas book for women problems</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>naveensippy</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-08-06 05:26:41</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-08-06 05:26:41</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>i believe any knowledge is supreme only if it is understood and put to use for the good of humanity.i do not find any cohesive order in this work, bright minds often tend to be neat and organised in area of expertise, unless the whole mission in the book is to confuse and waste peoples time like for instance writing all this...otherwise any hidden knowledge that requires code is only for sects and not for the use of majority</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>unhelpful</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>maishmaish</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-09-23 01:53:09</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-09-23 01:53:09</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Looking at the proficiency the lettering was made I dint believe its a hoax. It would take a person months of training to get the lettering so consistent for the whole manuscript. I do believe its a real language. I also do believe it contains information about the diagrams. Trying to disregard the text and only looking at the diagrams will not give much insight since any one drawing can be interpreted a thousand different ways. The theory of it being a coded text I also disregard since the coding mechanisms for the dated time was primitive but very effective back then. But master cryptographers with computers today will have no problem breaking the code.
I believe the reason it is so difficult to get meaning from the text is because the base system of the writing is something that is not known. 
Looking at the amateurish diagrams I believe it was done by some commoner who was unschooled but curious and therefore created his/her own writing system. This might indicate the "peasant" actually had a high intellect in a remote area who had no access to books or anyone who could write.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>My opinion its no hoax</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>ReBytes</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-10-06 21:32:27</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-10-06 21:32:27</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>picture number 31 just like cassava plant (manihot esculenta / manihot utilissima) in our real world, but the manuscript drawing is not better than nowdays artist works. i tought that the writer of this manuscript doesn't have great ability in scientific paintings especiallly in plant morphology. thats why we assumed that the pict of plant in this manuscript is not real.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>just my opinion...</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>sinduatlantis</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-10-08 16:38:23</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-10-08 16:38:23</createdate>
    <stars>3</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>the manuscript looks to me, like an old healers book. all plants are painted the way they look, at the perfect moment to crap them.
all important parts with the healing-drug are painted more colourful then the rest of it. then there are the pictures with woman.
to me they look like the renaissance idea of the living human body with its Humoral-Pathology after Galen. also used in the ancient astrology, so that the picture with the pregnant woman can be counted as  horoscopes for the babies born at that time. in the secret sript written, because church was fast with fire in that times...</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>possible meaning of the Voynich manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>AnnaTaliesin</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-10-22 17:13:47</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-10-22 17:13:47</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>This company Is finally making the voynich manuscript exact reproduction, foldouts and everything. Email ambushprinting@gmail.com for details, 
Or go to
Ambushprinting.squarespace.com</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Voynich manuscript reproduction</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Manosteel87</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-04-14 10:53:34</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-10-30 01:31:07</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>If languages have a way of rolling off the tongue when spoken properly; there should be some sort of rhythm to it. Picture instead of words these are musical chords. From my deduction of the first 30 pages there seems to be a pattern of the symbols indicating three "states" per symbol: these would be minor, mean and major. let me explain ... In English there are two symbols for each letter in the alphabet. Lets assume three things: there are letters, capitol letters and bold font letters indicating the importance of each letter. Each symbol has two characters. Every "word", indicated by spaces, is a musical chord.  For the first 30 or so pages I can see rythmatic patterns.  To me that would indicate either poetry, music or some other format displaying structure. Thereafter more symbols are added one or two at a time every so often. There are certain examples of similar format in modern languages such as vocabulary books for children and, (this may be a stretch for some) music. For example: A symphony starts off slow and steady then introduces new instruments and more complicated/richer sounds. later in the book the pages are started with "bold" letters such as AC/DC's 'thunder struck'. This isn't a solution by any stretch of the imagination but something to consider.

by the late 1300's there were multi level cyphers. perhaps the key-word is in the pictures or maybe even the first word on each page.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Consider this</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>sirmerlin860</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-11-28 06:20:59</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-11-22 02:40:43</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>The book, as many say , it looks like a book of botany.
When we open a book of botany what do we find ?
Description of plants with texts and images.
Properties. Scientific names and common use of plants. collection period. way of use. natural cycles.

These plants are not common, but they have one thing that is repeated in several pages : the flowers can contain one or more persons .

It seems that some of the pictures describe how to prepare special baths , uploading some flowers with pollen or substances. Are empty and are filtered with another plant. the liquid is used in more tanks for various purposes diluted in a liquid similar to water. They can be different concentrations , each with a different purpose.

The compositions included in the later flowers that are empty are described in the penultimate section of the book: the ingredients of the flowers are drawn in the first part of the book if you look carefully . the end can be indexed or treatment of these diseases bathrooms.

(sorry for my writing but I do not know good English and use translators )</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>One possible interpretation</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>RODONDO</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-11-24 13:36:53</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-11-24 13:36:53</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>[Blurb]START &gt; ALL PROGRAMS &gt; ACCESSORIES &gt; SYSTEM TOOLS &gt; CHARACTER MAP

That or some weird funny mathematics going on here for the biggest joke I've ever seen Lul. Eh, I know I seen some of those symbols somewhere but not in any spoken language that is for sure.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>This looks so familiar.</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>DivineMarker</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2013-12-04 08:22:32</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2013-12-04 08:22:32</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I looked at this a total of 15 minutes and intuitivitely gather, because engaged elsewhere while retiring, this could be a reverse engineering formula for plant distillation - elixer of life- or if men are involved a way to make gold
I prefer long life
Light
Why was dirt left off rooting
Hip hip hooray for the old gals
Or green man</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>A pox e-lapse Wayn icht - B's Whacts yes more please</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Mermadeinusa</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-01-26 06:15:15</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-01-26 06:15:15</createdate>
    <stars>1</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>At first ,while reading the 39 Clues series, I had no idea what was in the Voynich after reading this I understand how hard it is to read.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Voynich</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>The 39 Clues fan 879</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-02-03 01:20:59</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-02-03 01:20:59</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I may be completely wrong, but it appears to be a volume on grafting. The roots of all the illustrated plants seem to become more attached as the manuscript progresses. The root systems are separated in the early pages and seem to become connected as the the manuscript continues. This observation may simply point out a different illustrator, but seem to be a journal of progression of grafting (as many of the plants are unidentifiable). The astrology connections may simply be a guess into the connection of plant growth and celestial positions.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Plant Grafting</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>dustylane4</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-02-11 21:11:23</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-02-11 21:11:23</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Of people of the time.  Based on the pictures, and what I have read about the manuscript, it seems like an observation of the world, plants and people.  And how they interact.  I feel like the end, with very few pictures, seems to be a written conclusion of whoever wrote it, has come up to.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>I feel like it is an observation...</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>blur256</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-02-21 07:46:19</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-02-21 07:46:19</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I've been a Shaman for over 20 years now and have been studying DMT and it's role in out anthropology..

I don't think anyone has ever realized that the plants listed are all regional carriers of DMT from around the world..

The portion of the book containing formulas show a plant with DMT being mixed with a plant containing a high ammount of MAO inhibitors...

Ayulesca is listed as one of these formulas.. As well as my local regional brew of Mimosa flower/root and St. Johns Wart.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Hmmmm...</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Nashonic</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-03-06 00:38:48</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-03-06 00:38:48</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>5 stars for a quality copy.
...
Sadly, what appears to be a beautiful and interesting fake alchemical text in the spagyric tradition.  Please understand, I'm not saying it's a forgery - but a fake book; it has no notable connection to the alchemical process beyond the rather dreamlike connectivity of the unidentifiable plants in the plates.  Or perhaps it's an allegory of some kind with no known provenience, but that's doubtful - somewhere there should be parallel myth, tale or parable - yet unfortunately, there just isn't.  Logically, if there's a real code in the text, despite it's assumed complexity it would illuminate the paintings - but what could it possibly be shedding light on if there is no known cultural, mystical, philosophical, religious or scientific paradigm to compare it against?

For 700 years now, people have been complaining that the alchemists were a pack of wolves operating in a den of iniquity; perhaps here's some solid proof that at least one of them actually was.  Yet for all of that, it's a beautiful work of art.

Funny how we sometimes look for meaning even where there just might not be any. The act of which, of course, compels us subjectively to impart meaning on the object in question (ever stare at clouds?).  That's the very definition of "art".</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Quite Pretty. But...</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Angry_Ampersand</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-03-23 08:19:55</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-03-23 08:19:55</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Thank you आ२ाा,   It showed me the truth!!!!</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>🏣</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>☀️人天</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-04-09 21:27:44</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-04-09 21:27:44</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>The Voynich Manuscript authors wrote from around the Marble Caves of Ruskeala north of Sortavala in the Republic of Karelia, using mostly an old Finnish, Karelian, Estonian, or Ingrian dialect. The manuscript has a map of Sortavala and depicts plants that are only found in bogs in cold peat-accumulating areas. Its artist(s) painted plants the way an herbalist would--somebody gathering them for a use. Much of the text is a list of overwhelmingly Finno-Uralic names with some Dutch, Danish, French, and German tossed in now and then. The implements the gravid women are holding seem to center around midwifery. Similar artifacts have been found in Karelia (Sofporog) in 2001. The last pages feature surnames begun with a star and followed by first names. Baltic Finns have a tradition of banya or spa, and Finnish women have traditionally given birth in the sauna. Thus, the manuscript never was meant to have anything to do with alchemy. While the manuscript is authentic, the mystery surrounding it has been fabricated. For more, go to http://voynichbirths.blogspot.com</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>The mystery is the hoax, not the manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Pyat</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-05-27 00:20:29</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-05-27 00:20:29</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I took a look at every page closely...it's seems to me so done have travel through time and they are not from earth.he or she might be an so called explorer on plant,travel from planet to planet and the last destination might be on earth..where I think they see human using water for bathing and stuff..and thought we are one new species to them.why I said this is because if u see the picture from first page to the last,u will realize that about in the middle of the book there is a picture of girls so called bathing either near a river or somewhere that have a lot of plant surrounding it..the first page he or she is trying to tell his or her journey throughout planet and what he or she found..the circle drawing somewhere in the middle is very interesting because it's seems like there are other human world elsewhere ...the way they were using it are different...I hope I can read this and understand more..but that what I think the book all abt</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>My view on it</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Ayie1992</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2014-09-28 07:01:12</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-09-28 07:01:12</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>My name is   Sukhwant Singh   and  I have extensively researched in depth on MS-408 better known as the Voynichmanuscript.
I hope, my explanation will lead to resolving the Voynich manuscript once and for all.
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wmvmSCd2Jg0

This is absolute truth about MS408. ( Please watch this fully- Please do )
I have provided proofs for the whole alphabet comparing it with the existing written characters available from Multani, Khudabadi, Khojki, Landa, Mahajani languages.
Each character is defined, no guess work here.
If you study the history of Landa languages. The character hiding and mixing still happens in business communities in remote villages in Multan in Pakistan, to this day.
Please widen your knowledge as I have detailed as much as possible, There is no alternative to this, because this is the truth. All the researchers so far have guessed and fooled public. I want to emphasis this again "English does not have these sounds".
Its same way when you cannot understand the culture and language of another place, it's simple, do not make up something in the name of translation.
So far what injustice has been done to MS 408, it should stop.
Please research the history of the region, I have explained things which have evidence behind them.
If I have a mountain of gold, I will bet on it. Just because you don't understand, doesn't mean the  rest of the world doesn't either. 
I am not here to translate the whole book for the reason explained, but there are "No Experts" other than researchers on Landa Khojki, Multani, Sindhi mentioned in the explanation.
Nothing against anyone but You are absolutely not doing justice if you claim some culturally important book of someone else to be yours.
I am ready to debate word by word, because this is absolute truth, with evidence provided, No guess work here.


Please go through the video in full, hear the alphabet and see where the character came from, everything is explained word by word, including who could have written MS408.
The map is what I have explained in detail, including zooming in and clearly showing the cities in Uzbekistan. All that region including the rest down south didn't had any demarcation of countries which exist now. People used to travel as far as they could. Silk route was well traveled and passed through that region. 
Each word is explained with proof. If you cannot pronounce a word or unaware of culture of that region, I would suggest read more in depth from pages of history.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Voynich Manuscript Explained fully each character sound, Roma/Gypsies,Sindh/Pakistan,Uzbekistan silk route link</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>SukhwantSingh</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@sukhwantsingh</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2018-04-12 21:40:25</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2014-11-13 10:10:03</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Olha gente, o manuscrito é muito antigo, está faltando uma folha, pode ter certeza que nessa folha tem alguma tabela mostrando algo ou até mesmo mostrando a linguagem, ou pode ter sido um desenho de um diagrama perdido. Por que dizem que o manuscrito pode está faltando uma folha ou mais. Veja bem, ele está desgastado de tanto passar de pessoa em pessoa, sabe lá quantos séculos ele deve ter sobrevivido, posto em baús, em caixas e agora ele está bem descansado na biblioteca de manuscritos raros. Bem isso não importa, a minha duvida é sobre Jacobus a Tepenec (Jacobus Horcick) naquela época em que ele estava com Rodolfo II no Sacro Império Romano-Germânico, eu me perguntava: "Como Jacobus sabia fazer o elixir cura tudo para salva Rodolfo II de uma doença que quase o levou para a morte?" ,pra mim, Jacobus sabia sobre a linguagem do manuscrito, ele era um medico e com o manuscrito criou o elixir cura tudo, pois no final do manuscrito a frascos medicinais e plantas e nas partes finais do manuscrito tem grandes frases de como se estivesse ensinando a como fazer algo, bem eu não afirmo nada, só achei a versão de Jacobus muito interessante, criar um elixir cura tudo para salvar o Imperador Rodolfo II que realmente ganhou sua confiança naquela época. Jacobus sabia o que estava escrito no manuscrito, sabia sobre os diagramas, sabia tudo sobre as plantas e o que elas podiam fazer, como Rodolfo II pode ter dado o manuscrito a ele após a morte, pois Rodolfo sabia sobre o manuscrito também, mas sua história não focava no manuscrito, mas sim nas cidades e no seu irmão Matias. Bem, a linguagem está tão escondida que nem imaginamos onde está, o manuscrito falta folhas e nessas folhas podem ter as mesmas palavras, mas também figuras de tabelas e mais diagramas e talvez possa ter algo que conte sobre essa linguagem estranha. O que é tão agoniante pra mim, é que o manuscrito pode está incompleto, pode está faltando partes e mais desenhos ao meio. As letras no inicio do manuscrito estão meio apagadas, a pessoa escritora ou escritor que escreveu na primeira página, pode ter dado um dia ou uma semana para poder escrever a segunda. Já as últimas finais, as letras são nítidas, como se ele tivesse escrito na mesma hora concluindo o manuscrito em que a última página tem um desenho de uma mulher pequena meio apaga e as palavras finais ao lado, também meio apagadas. Só sei que Jacobus sabia do manuscrito, não sei como ele sabia, mas ele havia alguma ligação com natureza, se ele cuidava do jardim do Imperador Rodolfo, é por que Jacobus tinha alguma ligação com algo naquele jardim, ele tinha alguma ligação com a natureza, ou algo aproximado dele, eu me pergunto muitas coisas: "Será que Jacobus já sabia a linguagem?" Jacobus sabia também sobre os signos zodíacos e os diagramas, algo escrito sobre o sol, a lua, os dias, noite, dia, tarde, cada um diagrama, tendo o nome de estrelas e das constelações que me levou a pesquisar sobre Tycho. Tycho Brahe me chamou muito atenção sobre os diagramas solares, lunares e estrelares, Tycho criou um telescópio, descobriu um cometa igual a Galileu, morreu na mesma cidade onde sempre quando eu lia sobre as histórias interligadas ao manuscrito voynich, apertava na mesma tecla e essa tecla é a cidade de "Praga". Jacobu podia conhecer Tycho, algo sobre o manuscrito voynich podia estar ligado a Tycho também, Tycho criou um observatorio, ele nasceu em 1546 e morreu em 1601 quase perto da data em que o imperador Rodolfo morreu, a uma coincidência também que eu tenho é que a data em que Rodolfo II morreu (1612) parece a data em que M.Voynich descobriu o livro (1912). Tycho morreu em 1601, Rodolfo II morreu em 1612 e Jacobu em 1622, Tycho conhecia o Imperador Rodolfo II, pois uma vez o Imperador Rodolfo chamou Tycho para um serviço. Parece que há uma coisa faltando, parece que tem uma outra pessoa por detrás disso também, o Imperador podia ter contado a Tycho sobre o manuscrito voynich. As estruturas do manuscrito são do século XIV, há alguém por trás disso, tem uma outra pessoa, se soubessemos mesmo a pessoa que vendeu o manuscrito para o Imperador Rodolfo, tudo melhoraria, as coisas ficariam mais claras e abriria mais um espaço para descobrir sobre a linguagem. A versão de Jacobus me interessou muito e eu estava querendo descobrir a quarta pessoa, e essa quarta pessoa podia ser alguém não após Jacobus que deu o livro para seu amigo, não antes do Imperador Rodolfo, mas alguem que vivia em "Praga", antes do vendedor, alguem secreto que podia ter perdido o livro e o vendedor podia ter pegado para ter alguma ideia e a valiosidade. Provavelmente eu não sei onde quero chegar, mas só sei sobre Jacobus, ele sabia o que estava escrito no manuscrito voynich, ele tinha lido todo o livro escondido de Rodolfo ou não. Só Deus saberia o que estava acontecendo ao decorrer dessas décadas com o manuscrito, bem, mas eu acho que quem esteve com o livro não importa muito, o importante é saber mais sobre a linguagem. A questão de o manuscrito que possa ser uma fraude, eu não tenho que lhe dizer nada, por que a opinião das pessoas são validas, todas, mas quero dizer a vocês que quando eu estava vendo sobre algo que envolvia farsa e que envolvia Dee e Kepler, não se encaixava, sempre havia alguma coisa sobre o manuscrito que não se encaixava direito se ele era realmente uma farsa, primeiro por causa das datas, a tinta e a capa são do século XIV e não se encaixava na versão de Dee e Kepler ter dado o manuscrito para o Imperador Rodolfo. Roger Bacon morreu muito antes de o manuscrito ser criado no século, pois Roger morreu em dois século antes e como ele teria usado uma capa de carbono do século seguinte para fazer um manuscrito naquela década do século XII. Jacobus podia estar com manuscrito quando ele fez o elixir, podia haver plantas no jardim do castelo do Imperador o suficiente para ele fazer o elixir cura tudo, as plantas que podiam estar no manuscrito podiam estar no jardim, ou podia haver alguma comunicação com manuscrito na família de Jacobus. Agora o caso dos desenhos das mulheres, ainda é incompriencivel para mim, como mulheres pequenas e gravidas viviam em enormes vasos sanguineos, isso tambem podia estar ligado as plantas que está no manuscrito. Elas podiam estar fazendo parte de algo ou significando alguma coisa entre as plantas e o cáule e a raiz. O manuscrito pode ser um livro especial e tão especial quanto todos os manuscrito, é uma relíqua do passado e contando sobre todas as estrelas que rodeiam por cima da terra. Já os signos zodíacos, eu ainda irei análisar bem, já o grande e estranho mapa na página 86 do livro, aquilo eu realmente não tive quase nenhuma ideia, 9 células? Poderia parecer planetas interligados, no canto acima no terceiro globo do mapa, tem um castelo e isso me chamou muito atenção, um pequeno castelo que podia significar muito para um só desenho, o único desenho e uma única coisa em que reconhecemos naquele manuscrito e que podia significar uma paisagem de um castelo, as estrelas abaixo podiam significar plantas e um jardim estranho a frente de um castelo, a entrada do castelo no desenho não significa que está aberto e fechado, a cor azul significa que está escuro na entrada e na primeira torre do castelo a cima ao lado, está escuro também no topo, certificamos que no topo da primeira torre do castelo tem um buraco. Nossa, um castelo no núcleo de uma célula? Nisso ainda iremos precisas da linguagem para identificar cada desenho da teoria biológica do individuo. Pensei até nos noves planetas interligados, Júpter, Terra, Mercúrio, Marte, Saturno, Netúno, Vênus, Urâno e Jupter, pensei nos noves planetas e nas noves células, a Terra significaria o globo em que o castelo está. Já a célula ao meio, não tenho ideia, vai dar um bom tempo para compreendermos esse mapa e o que ele significa. Bem, temos um dever a fazer a analisar esse manuscrito direito. Cheguei até ir longe demais nesse assunto, em que o manuscrito tivesse duas chaves, eu descobri a primeira chave, a primeira chave é o elixir cura tudo, que eu pensei assim que se alguem decifrar todo o manuscrito e souber como fazer o elixir cura tudo, que esse elixir pudesse ferir pessoas e essas pessoas fossem Medicos. Elixir cura tudo, o remédio curador de todas as doenças se for possivel, seria o fim da Medicina com o elixir cura tudo pois um criptografo já falou que há plantas no méxico identicas as do manuscrito, cheguei a levar longe demais sobre isso, pois no livro mostra a como criar um elixir cura tudo. Eu não consigo identificar a segunda chave que está no livro, os diagramas, as mulheres e as estrelas. A única coisa que sei, é que as mulheres podem significar as estrelas. Mas a qualquer descoberta e duvidas extremamente pertubadoras e só compartilhar conosco aqui. Obrigado por ler, obrigado a todos vocês.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Um depoimento sobre Jacobus a Tepenec (Jacobus Horcick) e tudo o que eu sei.</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Kaliel</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2015-01-05 17:31:00</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2015-01-05 17:31:00</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>The skin is older but the writings are newer. Was it written by a left hand person or right hand one?, in those days you were not allowed to write with your Left hand so that explains the poor drawings of women It may be written by Leonardo da Vinci, he used both hands to write and draw. I think they used some kind of prisme that would reflect to other characters.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>MAYBE</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>treenataliet</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2015-01-14 15:17:24</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2015-01-14 15:17:24</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Clearly the work of Hieronymus Bosch

http://www.hieronymus-bosch.org/Garden-of-Earthly-Delights,-central-panel-of-the-triptych-large.html</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>voynich author</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>kennethshawn</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2015-03-16 21:53:28</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2015-03-16 21:53:28</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Looks like a science journal. First Botany, then Stars, Then people, then recipes. It's highly likely that it's a journal by a social sciences, the botany section describing plants and how they affect human behavior, the astronomy detailing how people are affected by the movements of the stars (Zodiacs and such) the third section detailing regular human activities and rituals, and the recipe book an idea for mixing the plants mentioned in the botany section.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Well...</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Javert999</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2015-07-06 23:41:09</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2015-07-06 23:41:09</createdate>
    <stars>3</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>The naked women in the river-like Things could be drawings of human Body parts. this could be a way to describe the human Body with the Knowledge of this time. first the manuscript describes plants to heal with and then astronomical things who they might thought to be of importance for healing at that time. and in the end the human body is explained in a way People might understand.

sorry for my poor english :)</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Women</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>aleeena</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2015-11-27 13:15:19</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2015-11-27 13:15:19</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>the book is in few parts: about plants, then circles, then women, then plants again, and finally notes that bring "diary" to my mind. or might have been just notes.

the person who wrote this book, could have been a herbalist or a doctor... for this to be solved we need a person who knows about plants and their uses. this already would help alot, to find out how shadowy part the plant-business is.

the circles... reminds of calendar but also could be about anything else that can be organized.
the few last disgusting circles ... each woman seems to have a name, surely proving, writer was greedy pervert who had wet dreams about different women and must have been kind of manic about it.

then we come more to the women, its like writer combined women and plants and is completely nuts. or he thought women are inside plants. or that they come from plants. or are related to them. anyway... it looks like most likely HE is trying to explain how plants work, and to keep it interesting, added naked women to demonstrate. 

also... the big map of 9 circles could have been a game board. or just map, or his children, or something else. the writer is dead, we will never know, unless he had descendant and has his sick mentality. perhaps, go and throw a copy of this book in each mental hospital, to people who are obsessed with plants and women. could help!

now there is herbalism again. are those pots for smoking? or medicine making? its not any wilder than that. could be spices, maybe he thinks those are best options for certain kind of plant to be stored/smoked/whatever.

then some notes. go to the country with highest similarities...

in any case, anyone with shitty imagination and dull, boring mind, like most people have, wich is disappointing, have no chance getting anything out of that book. 

just find a man, who knows his herbs. im not enough into herbs, and im not a man, so i cant really help. and i suppose most people dont know plants either. you need a specialist...</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>writer is most important</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>revohoxn</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2016-01-30 21:50:29</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2016-01-30 21:50:29</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>If you analyze the overall context of the writings and it's accompanying drawings, you can see that plants and women play into a theme.

Finally, some man discovered and understood how women think and their minds work.  He must've immediately thought to himself, "I'd better write this down for all men everywhere."

Hence, the Voynich Manuscript was born.  It easily explains the female mind.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Another possible explanation</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Tempest790</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2016-02-07 00:44:51</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2016-02-07 00:44:51</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Riabets M.A.
I deciphered the manuscript - a Scandinavian language - see here

http://voynichbook.pp.ua and http://voynichbook.inf.ua</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>I deciphered the manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>caxa</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2016-04-26 08:07:58</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2016-04-26 08:07:58</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I've been reading the book and I see that it's all about plants, to me it has nothing to do with astronomy or stars, a bit of imagination yes but nothing too far from reality. So what are the stars if not stars...for instance at some stage stars start to appear to be on the left of the page and following there's an entire paragraph for each type of star. there are several types of stars, they look similar but are different, which makes me think that the paragraph is describing what that star means. But also we start to see stars depicted with plants, these stars I believe to be seeds or seedlings. So when I then see the circles with firstly a face between two half moons I clearly see the moon cycle and same for the sun clearly depicted. It is the older story in human history there are some crops that are planted at growing moon and some other have to be after the day of frost. If you speak to a farmer that is 80+ they'll probably happily recite planting times according to weather and moon etc. for the crops they have grown. The circles are the cycles, the plants are plants and the women are the carriers of the seed be it the pods or the pollen etc. I see the planting seasons and the moon/sun cycles over the seedlings, then it gets into aries, taurus, libra etc. which could well mean months and planting seasons, then there is the liquid part which is the rainfall possibly nutrients, those women are carriers, each one of them carries a star or symbolises a stage of pregnancy. The part where there are many stars in a circle to me it could mean a few things like plant spacing or number of seeds that each star conforms to. or trying to think about what those many stars mean, for example some crops such as garlic go on for 8 months so if you were to plant say 4 garlics a month you would end up never without garlic. To me this entire book is only and solely about plants and plant physiology. I can recognise many plants with a bit of imagination. There's a great explanation on roots for each depiction as well as the top text is also depicted with the top of the plants. Also there are word sequences that I noticed repeat at roots and some that repeat at the tops which makes me think that if one possibly tries to match symbols to images without applying a meaning to them and just imagining what they may refer to in relation to the picture it kind of flows in a weird way hard to explain without sounding looney but this book is a big puzzle it not was meant  to be translated but to be understood beyond language...visualise and apply meaning.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>I've got a point to make</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>onethousandtwohundredeightynine</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2016-05-31 12:24:39</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2016-05-31 12:24:39</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Hi dear fellas,
I found something interesting while going through this manuscript. I am not sure whether someone mentioned this previously or not. 

While am going through each page and illustration of plants and human, kind of beings were done by some amateur painter. I believe this manuscript was prepared by more than 2 people. One person might have illustrated the picture that was painted on the page and the other person simply drew the pictures. 

This logic made me to think that- How come a beautiful handwriting person can be a bad painter? 
And also I see some imprints of paintings on the backside of each page, it clearly indicates that paintings were done 1st and context about the paintings were wrote later on. I also felt that some of the flower paintings resembled that native Asian flowers esp one picture resembled the LOTUS flower leaf.

I am not sure what was written in that book but it clearly says the manuscript was prepared by more than 1 person.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Illustrator and writer</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Navyarao</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2016-08-09 06:26:19</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2016-08-09 06:26:19</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I just noticed all the pots illustrated next to the pictures of the plants (pages 161 and 174). Does the book use different pots to illustrate the roots looking the same (notice the legs of the pots) or are they just random containers used to store those roots?

So what they've illustrated there might have been real pots people used at the time and area of the writing (Near East etc.). This is just an idea but all those small people next to the organic-looking things might have been the "plant-souls", describing birth/death of plants (in this case pollination and possibly other related things).</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>A couple of ideas</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>collytus</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2016-08-21 17:17:10</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2016-08-21 17:17:10</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>The words seem to be rather short 4-7 letters. There seems to be no prepositions or postpositions what I can tell at least. There are distinctive patterns of words that keep on repeating. The resulting text seems to be rather artificial. Maybe code with made up letters and missing key to decipher?</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>My first impressions about the language</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Timo T.</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2016-08-22 11:59:22</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2016-08-22 11:59:22</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>As it is said the book like this written in latin would have been valuable at the time. So there is some rich duke who wants to seem intellectual and own a scientific book. Somebody hears about this and sees a possibility to make money. He pays a bookmaker to make a book that looks like scientific book but written in gibberish so that he duke won't know what the book is abut. Book seems legit so he pays a good money and brags to his friends as he owns a scientific book. So that's what this book is. A book made to look valuable. If you see the text there's a lot of same kind of words repeating. This is usual for made up languages.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Mystery solved</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>jeremyisland</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2016-09-03 12:46:51</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2016-09-03 12:46:51</createdate>
    <stars>3</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Each time I have done DMT, I have seen some of those plants. Whether it is only inches away, but on a different vibration, or some where across the universe transported instantly, I believe the Voynich Manuscript is describing a very real place, with many similarities to those on Earth and sharing some possible "laws" of the universe looking at the pages that suggest Zodiac/Horoscope charts, and Galaxy maps.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>I have seen some of those plants</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>meyerdel</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2017-01-10 06:04:03</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2017-01-10 06:04:03</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>http://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-22975809

A fine overview of the object, controversy and learned, serious opinions on actual significance. 
However, the article ends... as the mystery continues.....

"After this study, any new support for the hoax hypothesis should address the emergence of this sophisticated structure explicitly. So far, this has not been done.

"There must be a story behind it, which we may never know," Dr Montemurro adds.

+++++

Very cool to have a "personal copy" in pdf available here on archive.org</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>BBC.com Science Overview of the VM</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Den NC USA</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2017-01-24 15:35:16</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2017-01-24 15:35:16</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Muito legal ter este pdf disponível aqui no archive.org
Vlw
Marcos</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Copy of The Voynich Manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Marcos Santos</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2017-03-04 00:17:10</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2017-03-04 00:17:10</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Thanks a lot for providing this book. The   image  quality and other info  is in the form very nice  .</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>best job by u</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>MUJAFFAR</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@mujaffar</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2017-11-24 18:34:32</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2017-11-24 18:34:32</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Here is a hint. What do a Venus fly trap, the birth of Venus painting and the songs "in bloom" and "kiss by a rose" have in common. Something like Carl Jung and the truman show :)


Cragerdoiron@gmail.com</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Email me.</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Morning glory88</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@morning_glory88</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2018-03-09 18:04:10</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2018-03-09 18:04:10</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I printed the front &amp; back cover on plain white paper and held it up to light. It looks like nothing when it's right side up but when you flip it upside down looking at it with light behind it you can see drawings all over it in different spots. Both front &amp; back cover flipped upside down looking at it with light behind the sheet.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Can anyone check this</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Benjamin J Servick</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@benjamin_j_servick</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2018-03-11 03:02:35</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2018-03-11 03:02:35</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>it seems to be an altered version of the language syriac</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>the language</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>michael patric hennessey</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@michael_patric_hennessey</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2018-03-19 04:04:58</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2018-03-19 04:04:58</createdate>
    <stars>3</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>What if this is an unknown/lost work of Leonardo DaVinci? I don’t have any insight into the text but the illustrations look like the work of a painter or an artist. And I actually read somewhere that the artistic renderings of all the women in baths actually seem to depict the structure and function of different bodily organs. If that’s the case then the author had a working knowledge of biology. Food for thought...</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Lost work of DaVinci?</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Meg.marie225</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@meg_marie225</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2018-04-13 02:19:48</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2018-04-13 02:19:48</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Seeing the struggle of words or text between the drawings tells about the writer have first captured the visual elements from his close observation. He has seen the plants, women, stars and have first drew the picture.Later like his auto biography he started writing about it by his research between the drawings. The author has managed to group the individual papers together to form a journal as an archive of his research.As the texts are of in a single line it could be written by a women where most of the elements mentioned depicts to give a life or some form of life.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Work of a Researcher</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>HPalakat87</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@hpalakat87</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2018-08-26 13:36:26</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2018-08-26 13:36:26</createdate>
    <stars>3</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Dear Intellectuals of light bearing science,

Today I am honored to inform you that the Voynich Manuscript has been finally deciphered.
To date, scientists, historians, mathematicians and linguists have struggled to decipher the manuscript. However, the mystery has finally been put to rest. ATA Team Alberta (ATA) has deciphered and translated over 30% the manuscript. Currently, a formal paper of the philological study was submitted to an academic journal in John Hopkins University.
Here is the link for uncovering the greatest mysterious manuscript and the logic behind
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p6keMgLmFEk
Here is a much more detailed one but unfortunately this is in Turkish..I will translate this one in English as soon as possible.
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Y5ckHIpqGnY</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Voynich Manuscript Revealed !</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>XXVII</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@xxvii</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2018-09-01 14:19:00</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2018-09-01 14:19:00</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>THANK GOD GOOGLE DIDN'T GET THEIR HANDS ON THIS BEAUTIFUL MANUSCRIPT

EXCELLENT IN ALL WAYS</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>ROBERTO de MEDICI  -  AFABIntl@comcast.net</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>rgo33062</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@rgo33062</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-01-19 13:31:12</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-01-19 13:31:12</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>i tried to translate some of these words used scots gaelic, for example word "saillg"  means in english "fat".
ollag - holly (flower)
ollarag - wool</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>possible to translate</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Madbroandrew</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@madbroandrew</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-03-17 17:36:17</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-03-17 17:36:17</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>thanks</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>hiiii</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>aser1981</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@aser1981</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-03-19 23:30:14</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-03-19 23:30:14</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>I think that this manuscript is written in ancient Berber language is somewhat similar to Amazigh language also some of the existing plants are present in abundance in Egypt
this link told you what i say 
https://barhoumadel.files.wordpress.com/2009/11/d8b4d983d984-d8a2d8aed8b1-d984d986d8a8d8a7d8aa-d8a7d984d8aed8b1d988d8b9.jpg
http://www.canaryfans.com/upload/3_11/50194626.jpg
In the electronic version of the manuscript page 13 and 14 there is a similarity between the plant in the manuscript and its reference to the link</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>We try to look deeply</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>MRNet</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@mrnet</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-03-29 18:32:49</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-03-29 18:28:01</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>The language of the manuscript has been deciphered! remains to wait for the full translation in the future :) I will add that this is a proto-Romanesque language whose words can be found in many modern Portuguese languages, Italian Galician, etc. 

https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02639904.2019.1599566</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>decrypted</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>cdq18341@cndps.com</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@cdq18341_cndps_com</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-05-19 09:40:41</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-05-19 09:40:41</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>No, the Voynich Manuscript has not been cracked. Not yet. Cheshire's supposed solution seems to be incorrect. The University of Bristol has retracted their press release mentioning his work. 

https://www.theguardian.com/science/2019/may/17/university-backtracks-on-disputed-voynich-manuscript-theory

https://arstechnica.com/science/2019/05/no-someone-hasnt-cracked-the-code-of-the-mysterious-voynich-manuscript/

https://voynichportal.com/2019/05/16/cheshire-reprised/</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Re: decrypted</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Ben in Seattle</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@ben_in_seattle</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-05-24 10:36:33</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-05-24 10:36:33</createdate>
    <stars>0</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>LOL, I thought so they only made assumptions no real explanations. Maybe some 'strange' things...
But it has not been cracked, far from being cracked without some 'eyeopeners'!</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>NOT CRACKED!</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>DrunKnJSD</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@drunknjsd</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-07-12 03:27:59</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-07-12 03:27:59</createdate>
    <stars>4</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Obviously this is a hoax. This is the rituals and purification rules that Israelí women used  for cleanness and medications. The color of some flowers and event are misrepresented because Israelí people were very religious; colors themselves had meaning. Like water color meant a mass of people, and red mean not pure, black mean evil, and so on.

This book is to teach woman how to believe, work, purified, and cleanliness.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Voynich fraud</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Scoaband</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@scoaband</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-10-03 18:54:47</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-10-03 18:54:47</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>If one backs up from trying to crack its language you can see that its in three different languages.. one is picture language, 2nd is plant language and third is most important, it is star constellations language.. Its actually telling you a story you are not ready to here..its repeating the same message on every page too..</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>completely readable</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>creamcorncrazy</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@creamcorncrazy</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-10-08 16:40:27</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-10-08 16:40:27</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>How can i see it in reality where is it situated?</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>question</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Mr.A1</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@mr_a1</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2019-11-13 17:28:00</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2019-11-13 17:28:00</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Some plants look like sweet potatoes. Some plants for making water. Water had been reused. The Sun and Moon inside of the earth.</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>It looks like the world under the earth.</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>HuiLihero</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@huilihero</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2020-03-20 03:37:28</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-03-20 03:37:28</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>用來記錄這個職務的成長過程或是分布圖
C可能代表種子
蝴蝶符號代表葉子=leaf=lf圖案類似</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>也許是象形文字</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>士林林先生</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@user_24292</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2020-03-22 08:57:47</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-03-22 08:57:47</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>127頁是不是雙魚座？旁邊都是人格分析
後面的幾頁也是星座的人格？</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>127 頁是星座嗎？</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>YJJ328</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@yjj328</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2020-04-12 08:46:25</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-04-12 08:46:25</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Okuyoruz lakin indiremiyorum beceremedim sanırım yardım edin. Nasıl indirebilirim kitapları</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Burdaki pdf veya okunan kitapları nasıl indirebilirim</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Elit80</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@elit80</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2020-04-19 11:12:32</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-04-19 11:12:19</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewbody>Schaut für mich aus wie Mohn... nach meinem Kräuterwissen könnten die farbigen Teile der Pflanzen auf deren Verwendbarkeit hindeuten- zur Sprache... es gab ja immer auch Sprachen ohne Vokale?!?, wo sich die Vokale als Anhängsel der Konsonanten ergaben- das könnte ja auch auf Artikel und sonstige Füllwörter zutreffen, die dann einfach weggelassen werden können- vielleicht handelt es sich ja um eine Schrift  aus der Frauenheilkunde aus einem Land, wo die Frauen nicht wertgeschätzt wurden/werden?!?
Oben auf Seite 139 springen mir quasi Eierstöcke mit einer Gebährmutter entgegen😉</reviewbody>
    <reviewtitle>Page 33/139</reviewtitle>
    <reviewer>Karin Kalyani</reviewer>
    <reviewer_itemname>@karin_kalyani</reviewer_itemname>
    <reviewdate>2020-04-19 11:31:39</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-04-19 11:31:39</createdate>
    <stars>5</stars>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Diary of a schizophrenic</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>The work has the character of a schizophrenic. Despite all appearance of intelligence, discipline, determination, and proliferation, it is utter nonsense.  </reviewbody>
    <stars>0</stars>
    <reviewer>Ted3</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2020-07-24 16:19:07</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-07-24 16:19:07</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@ted3</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>120页中间图案可能是一天的时间</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>120页中间图案像是一天的时间。有点像是时间表，有月亮和太阳，白天和黑夜。另外文字的表象形式有点奇怪，我用镜子照着看觉得更合理，以及有些类似拼音法，如果用英语和拉丁文或者其他什么的不合理，因为长短字符有点少。</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>gudizi</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2020-07-31 17:41:16</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-07-31 17:31:03</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@gudizi</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Graft</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Looks like plant grafting from a poets point of view. Elaborately done leaves n flowers. Obviously that’s the main theme of the book. Possibly attributes of the grafted plant with health benefits </reviewbody>
    <stars>2</stars>
    <reviewer>Meymary</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2020-08-07 18:56:58</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-08-07 18:56:58</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@meymary</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Botany journal</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Obviously the creator is a better writer than a painter. Look at the mouse/squirrel eating a leaf on page 50. I feel its a journal of a botany/herb enthusiast in a now-extinct language and probably extinct plants as well.</reviewbody>
    <stars>3</stars>
    <reviewer>vid_06</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2020-09-13 13:32:22</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-09-13 13:32:22</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@vid_06</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Pg 170</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>The plant picture at the most right looks similar to a plant called "Actaea Pachypoda"</reviewbody>
    <stars>2</stars>
    <reviewer>CSChow</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2020-09-20 14:32:46</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2020-09-20 14:32:46</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@cschow</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>المخطوطة الغامظة</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>حقا مخطوطة غاممضة ومجهولة اللغة وكل ما فيها من الامور في تاريخنا العربي القديم لا يوجد معها أي شيء لنستدل بها ويبقى الامر في ايدي المتخصصين</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>guerguit-amar</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-01-06 19:59:53</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-01-06 19:59:53</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@guerguit-amar</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Nice</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Good to know actually important things are on the archive and it's not just pirated stuff.</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>SomethingIGuess2019</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-01-26 03:14:52</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-01-26 03:14:52</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@somethingiguess2019</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>It is a book of gardener and a herble researcher who have describe his research</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>In this book I see herb and herb sketch of different types herble plant I think he or she observing this plant very carefully and write in his own language which is not understand by me but there are some symbol which represents some kind of odd thing in this plant, I think this is research book of a scientist research on plant. </reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>Devraj Baidya</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-03-08 15:16:19</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-03-08 15:16:19</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@devraj_baidya</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>MissionImpossible</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Early Islamic, around 1100 to 1200. This period known for studying and transcribing ancient Greek medical works such as Dioscorides, a Greek physician. Early Islamism's are also known for calligraphy, or stylized writing, and this writing is likely an ancient lost form of Arabic or stylized ancient Greek. Also noting the restriction of religious figural imagery in Islam lead to a strong use of artistic depictions of flowers and plants. See.. "Preparing Medicine from Honey" for artistic similarities as well as also being a dispersed manuscript of Arabic translation of De Materia Medica of Dioscorides, Baghdad. 
Solid evidence from early 12th and 13th century Muslim astrology is featured in the back of the manuscript nearly identical to "Bowl with Courtly and Astrological Signs" from The Metropolitan Museum of Art. </reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>rayjay662</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-04-06 05:55:35</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-04-06 05:27:32</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@rayjay662</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Has anyone copied the script by hand</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>I find the rare character sequences not surprising when I hand write the script.  It feels like a cursive stroke that is fun, but also, routine.  So much so that it is almost desirable to write, but with speed and little thought to the purpose.  I agree it feels Islamic, but has a structure of Latin imo.  As if the opening paragraph is a question or assertion that would be well known at the time.  Several of the characters look different, but feel similar.  A couple glasses of wine and they'd be the same; though the sharp changes in the stroke vs smooth changes, make me feel like these are not the same the characters.  

Additionally, this "feels" like a scientific log book.  Strikingly, the root system of each plant is focused; the upper portions of the plants seem surreal.  I see a young person doing this who is learning, but bored at times.  Not artistic, but observant.  The first page is the key imo.  It has an introduction, then two distinct paragraphs representing unsteeped and steeped analyses.  The extended special script in the steeped (third paragraph), look to me like a shorthand for representing emulsion time or magnitude of a measurment (e.g., aroma, length of brew, heat applied, etc.).</reviewbody>
    <stars>4</stars>
    <reviewer>ChrisBMD</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-05-02 20:25:16</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-05-02 20:09:21</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@chrisbmd</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Page 140</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>生物學
140頁 左右兩位女生 中間一位女生
很像是子宮（uterus）右下的圖是腸道（intestinal tract）</reviewbody>
    <stars>4</stars>
    <reviewer>Mitty Hu</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-05-13 15:37:55</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-05-13 15:37:55</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@mitty_hu</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Renaissance scam of ancient texts or fake diagram of what’s in the new world.</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>The carbon dating on the vellum is 16th 15th century and many believe it was written around the same time. During this period the new world was just discovered and the rediscovery of ancient knowledge was starting the renaissance. A book like any other, full of what looks like medicinal, herbal, and spiritual diagrams would of been unbelievably intriguing/ meaning it would be worth big big money. Many forget that some of our most important historical texts come from singular copies that were found and preserved during this exact time period; Cicero, Lucretius, Tacitus. Also new world expeditions were doing crazy fundraising during this same period, and peoples imaginations were running wild with what was there to be found in the ancient texts and in the new world. This book intrigues us to this day because that’s what its purpose was from the beginning. Just give me a bunch of gold and you can know all these ancient secrets or all this new world knowledge!!!</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>Brocabe</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-06-26 02:07:00</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-06-26 02:07:00</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@brocabe</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Idon't think it's about a women health or spring</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>It's a little bit religious and astronomical, but it's main subject is biology. There are numerous ancient books in eastern world that mixing religion and biology, also they mixed religion and astronomy. So my opinion is that the book is describing plant's biology with many exemplifications and associating them with religion and astronomy, and totalizes them with the help of woman characters to understand them.</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>booming1235</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-07-16 16:04:27</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-07-16 16:04:27</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@booming1235</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>More Like The Extraterrestrials Manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>What if this was an a being visiting worlds and taking scientific notes of everything they come across. Some of the plants look very alien to me.</reviewbody>
    <stars>4</stars>
    <reviewer>romeoquid</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-07-28 00:40:21</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-07-28 00:40:21</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@romeoquid</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Fascinating but not much of a mystery to me</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>During a lull in the workday I decided to watch a youtube video that caught my attention with a picture of a giant human skeleton that had wings.....yes I know it's a fake pic but I just had to investigate.  Anyway, the video was interesting as it was about the 15 strangest discoveries of all time.  Of course the antikythera mechanism was on it, something about a SE Asian family dynasty named the Travancores, and then this book-- the Voynich Manuscript. After it was over, I started down the rabbit hole of the "VM" for short. 
 When I found this page with the actual digital images I flipped through each page as if reading it and couldn't help but feel that book was familiar to me. The structure of the handwriting, the drawings, the shape of the letters...then it hit me. 
This book isn't fake, it's not chinese, and it's not islamic. This is what we would call a "lost" notebook or journal of a young Leonardo Da Vinci. Before you dismiss me, hear me out.... we know Leonardo set about on his own very early in life (early teens) we know he was a curious youth with exceptional intelligence, and we know just about nothing of his 'wandering years'.
I went looking for samples of Leonardo's handwriting just to see for myself if the "VM" resembled Leonardo's and if the "VM" could be a sort of shorthand written backwards which he is famous for doing and came across this post: http://www.edithsherwood.com/voynich-handwriting/index.php
Take a look at it and read what Ms. Sherwood has to say. I believe she is on to something and it's worth exploring further.  
</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>BeBeDee</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2021-11-06 01:32:14</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2021-11-06 01:32:14</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@bebedee</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>the letters</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>65% a combination of old Bulgarian linear and Thracian letters</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>Malinas</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2022-01-16 23:42:20</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2022-01-16 23:42:20</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@malinas</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>THE AGRICULTURE OF THE NABEATEANS</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>THE AGRICULTURE OF THE NABEATEANS’ THE NAME OF THE AUTHOR
of the Voynich Manuscript is
IBN WAHSHIYYAH the Nabataean
 

Ibn Wahshiyyah the Nabataean was a tenth century Persian agriculturalist, historian, linguist and translator who was born in Qussayn and translated ‘The Voynich Manuscript’, also known as: ‘THE AGRICULTURE OF THE
NABEATEANS’ or ‘Ms 408’ or ‘al-Fil-āha al-nabatiyya’ into the Persian or Farsi language in 904 ad.

Translated into Persian The Voynich Manuscript translates an old record of a sea voyage in search of medicinal herbs and perfumed oils and resins called attars.

Other names Ibn Wahshiyyah was known by are:

Bin Wahshih Ahmad bin Abubekr
AKA Ibn Wahshiyyah the Nabataean
Ahmad bin Abubekr bin Wahshih
Abu Bakr ‘Ahmad bin ‘Ali and many others.
https://www.voynichmanuscript2021.com/
</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>No Business</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2022-02-10 18:04:53</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2022-02-10 15:57:55</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@no_business</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Interesting, but doesn't seem like something wildly profound</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>I've gone through the book and pondered about it and have several thoughts, some are in regards to previous suggestions.

As a first thing that hit me was "is this scrip LTR?" after a some more it seems that not, but something about it, just didn't sit right with me - then the comment, that it is perhaps a notebook of Leonardo Da Vinci who was left handed make me thing it's possible that if not a LTR language, it was perhaps written by a left handed writer.

Something about it also hits me as a conlang that is a constructed language, which quite possibly the author was the only speaker and wanted it to remain this way.

However, given how shitty the drawings are I find it very unlikely it would be his, unless he perhaps used his right  hand to draw and a left hand to write. There is a degree of discrepancy between the drawings (which somehow look like a children's drawings in a way) and the script, which is quite neat and straight. 

Another thing which makes me wonder if it's Leonardo's is - would a likely gay guy spend a huge section of a possibly private notebook with insane amount of depictions of naked women? Idk, I find it strange.

Conceptually the first and the last part seem almost exactly like a herbarium book (except the plants are drawn) - there is an effort to show the roots etc,so whoever drew them had to have pluck them from the ground and examined. So somebody with interest in nature.

I must again stress the shittines of execution and a little schizophrenic nature of it as there are all those pictures of plans - that had to be drawn first - then the text was added next to it and around it - however it fit. So that doesn't seem too well thought out.

I am no expert on Leonardo Da Vinci, but given his genius and the known works, this doesn't seem like something he would make - unless perhaps in some very odd state of mind and as an experiment e.g. what if I try to write a book that's in my language, with my right hand and as a reflection or something bizarre like that.

At moments I wondered if perhaps the pictures weren't drawn by a child of the author in some sort of cute collaboration. There are parts that seem a bit like that's not likely (the zodiac circles for example) but again, no idea.

I do like how the script looks and wonder what the language is really. The section with women in "bath tubs" and pipes are really freaky - somehow I can't decide if it's like all women hot springs or some weird women breeding laboratory.

The star looking things have those strings attached to them - makes me wonder wtf? Perhaps those are flowers not stars or sometimes they are flowers sometimes they are stars.




</reviewbody>
    <stars>4</stars>
    <reviewer>tamiyo</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2022-02-19 18:54:22</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2022-02-19 18:54:22</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@tamiyo</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>The plants are the key</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Very fun puzzle. In case anyone actually wants to decipher this; I suggest getting acquainted with the scientist behind the Eden Project.</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>Tina McCollaum</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2022-06-15 08:13:44</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2022-06-15 08:13:44</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@tina_mccollaum</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>I figured out what this book is all about &amp; My Evidence is Undeniable</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Mysterious Voynich Manuscript Decoded by me Evidence=Why is Patent Technology by 2inventors &amp; 2Different eras Nikola Tesla&amp; Mysterious Hyperspace Inventor St Clair JohnQ doing on same page?   &amp; Nature Image off My recording Closely matches Nikola Patent on that page &amp; Nikola “There is no subject more captivating, more worthy of study, than nature. To understand this great mechanism, to discover the forces which are active,&amp; the laws which govern them, is the highest aim of the intellect of man.”
Crazy how Academia and Super computers could not figure this book out but I did just from one page I have the key that unlocks the whole thing pretty much in this one social media post of mine &amp; Here is the answer that should put me down in the History books as solving this. It is my original find &amp; its hard to Deny. 


https://truthsocial.com/@OurCloakedUnseenWorld/108637428105180463</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>Our Cloaked Unseen World</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2022-07-28 13:40:01</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2022-07-28 13:40:01</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@our_cloaked_unseen_world</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Isn't the paragraph relatively new</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Interesting!

The document has paragraphs. Which came into being in 16th century, based on a Google search? And this has paragraphs like we know today, with spacing et al.

Likely to be a hoax.</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>SonaliSingh</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2022-09-06 13:54:53</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2022-09-06 13:54:53</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@sonalisingh</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Weird.</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Notice that page 206 is not at all the same writer. Even the ink looks different. Find that weird .
</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>MariaVDE</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2022-09-11 18:39:47</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2022-09-11 18:39:47</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@mariavde</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>It's a Mid-Evil Witch Grimoire</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>     I just skimmed through the manuscript and in my opinion I believe as a Pagan &amp; a practicing Witch that this is a Witches  Grimoire, either for personal use or within a Coven. And I also believe the words are written using some form of the Witch's alphabet. </reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>Frankie Rumery</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2022-10-11 06:02:45</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2022-10-11 06:02:45</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@frankie_rumery</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Исследования анатомии человека во времена церковных гонений.</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Интересную особенность заметил во время просмотра манускрипта. После просмотра с середины и до конца, то если вернуться в начало, то растения уже не кажется ими. Больше похоже на системы организма и их срезы. Страницы с женщинами похожи на кровеносную систему и внутренние органы, а многие растения представляют собой системы человека и нервные узлы. Если книге действительно около 500 лет, то как раз попадаем под активные церковные гонения исследователей и запрет на изучения "тела божьего". Да и в какой-то моент было чувство что весь текст был переписан с другого источника, за пару подходов. так что если это средневековый доктор, который под видом написания ботанического атласа, создавал атлас тела человека и работы его систем, то это просто гениально. И кстати момент с девушками и козлом, такое чувство что это описание взросления девушки, от малышки, до полового созревания и менопаузы. Но это всего лишь глупые мысли, пришедшие мне в голову, когда Я не мог уснуть. Завтра снова на работу, лечить детей, а мне не спится и  Я пишу ревью на русском, которое скорее всего даже не опубликуется. Если удруг ты был любопытен и перевел и прочитал это, спасибо тебе друг. И помни, иногда лучше высказать даже самую тупую мысль, которая в итоге может оказаться спасительным кругом, чем молчать и ждать пока проблема не захлестнет тебя с головой. Успокой свои мысли и выпей пива, за неизвестного тебе русского доктора, cheers!))</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>DMITRY Hunt</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2023-07-03 22:54:52</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2023-07-03 22:54:52</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@dmitry_hunt</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Voynich</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Homunculi?</reviewbody>
    <stars>0</stars>
    <reviewer>Akchill27</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2023-07-16 18:53:41</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2023-07-16 18:53:41</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@akchill27</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>IT WAS A TRAVELER</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>It was a traveler. Who was looking for plants .He painted plants, trees and algae.
He drew the components of the tree, not the whole tree. That is, a stump, roots, leaf, bud. Probably didn't know how to draw or didn't see the point in it. He drew to memorize the object and recognize the constituent parts of the plant. Lots of algae. Women who bathe in blue and green water this time of year. Green water is the time of water blooming, algae appear. He drew bathing times, rivers and lakes, places where to find algae. Stars and horoscopes, he wrote a map of how to find a plant, tree or algae. The starry sky is a landmark. Most likely the number of
Steps or meters need to go in one direction or another to find the plant he needs. He moved through the starry sky to find a plant or a river, a lake in which there were algae.</reviewbody>
    <stars>0</stars>
    <reviewer>Alexey888</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2023-07-26 19:23:06</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2023-07-26 19:23:06</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@alexey888</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>It seems to be the Glagolitic Alphabet!!!</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>The book is certainly fascinating. It contains written text that seems to be in the same Glagolitic alphabet, one of the oldest Slavic alphabets. The presence of ornate drawings and the formatting suggest that this might be a religious or liturgical manuscript, which would be common for texts written in this alphabet.

The Glagolitic was used to write Church Slavonic, the liturgical language of Slavic churches. These texts were typically of a religious nature, including copies of the Bible, hymns, prayers, and liturgical texts.

Given the specialized nature of the Glagolitic and Church Slavonic, an exact translation and complete understanding of the content would require an expert in Slavic paleography and Slavic religious studies.

However, the beauty and historical significance of this manuscript are undeniable. Manuscripts like this serve as a window into the cultural and religious history of the Slavic people and the spread of Christianity in Eastern Europe. Ideally, to obtain a more detailed translation or interpretation, one should seek an expert or academic institution with expertise in Slavic studies or paleography to truly determine if the text is Glagolitic.</reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>Fábio Silveira446</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2023-10-26 16:06:52</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2023-10-26 16:06:52</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@f_bio_silveira446</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>Has anyone notice the names of the women?</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>I notice some of the names on the top of page 80 (146 of the PDF)  appear on the paragraph below in a way that seams to be telling some story. It seam the book is about stories of fairies that live in a magical garden inside a castle.</reviewbody>
    <stars>0</stars>
    <reviewer>Troxtor Studios</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2023-12-01 06:46:58</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2023-12-01 06:46:58</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@troxtor_studios</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>The characters form a picture on each written page.</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>I looked at the book from back to front. 
The pages show 3 dimensional pictures.
It may not be a language, it may be an art form.</reviewbody>
    <stars>0</stars>
    <reviewer>lindah99999h</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2024-05-08 05:05:36</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2024-05-08 05:05:36</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@lindah99999h</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>???</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>F c c i/v e/z . g k a l . e/z  . a h a t z . c e o c b . e o a . ___z z . g k o z . c l o z e . q/z o q/z a . c k e a et . oqa 
 first two lines of the manuscript p. 1   ?
 i still dont understand the hand writing the writer of the manuscript may traveled through arabic places as the writing style looks like a mix of hindi , eng , arabic . 
funny right ?  </reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>vony4gemanuscript</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2024-06-04 11:59:40</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2024-06-04 11:59:40</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@vony4gemanuscript</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>vineyard; my theory of the Voynich Manuscript</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>A very old vineyard that dates at the very least to the Alexandrian period and quite possibly to Solomon.  "Solomon had a vineyard that you would have to pay a thousand pieces of silver for," the actual reference is in the Nabre bible in the Song of Songs, chapter 8 verse 11-14.  
Noah also had a vineyard, and by the way the old trellis from Noah's vineyards are more than likely now petrified wood; An old fence row, and that's my final answer!  But that's another theory about the Ark of Noah.

The theory about a traveler and a Witches Grimoire in reference to the Voynich manuscript isn't too far off I think. The Story of the house of the wind from the Vangelo Della Strega tells the story of a wandering grape vine and a little girl who grew up under the heavy hand of the Church.   Through out the whole text of the Vangelo, not only the story about the Peasants house or the House of the Wind, but also the references to Le Vecchia herself could be translated into the Gospel of the vine.

Until previously there was not a lot of explanation given for the Gospel of the Witches other than they were Italian witches and I think the Voynich Manuscript may be a part of a families lost heritage.   That's the theory I've been working on concerning the manuscript.   

The Voynich manuscript written in some kind of code, therefore in essence is "The Gospel of the Vines," the history of the vines themselves, the History of a families possession of those vines, and the fauna that they bring in with them.
 
The fauna seems kind of alien because Grape Vines in particular have a history of bringing in the fauna around them to better accommodate their surroundings if they are left untamed, in other words there will be similar shapes and structure of the leaves and roots and also the vining capabilities amongst the complimentary plants that come with them.  They learn to spread, climb, and grow in similar patterns including in rows and are capable of changing or variegating the other plants that grow with them.
 
The "pilgrim" vines are not exactly tame they are pilgrim vines after all, and so they do "wander around"  a bit. 
However, they are not entirely wild either, once upon time they had a caretaker who must have cared a lot;  I'm starting to sound a lot  like Elton John!

Most of those Alien plants can probably be identified to some degree even in their rudimentary form, if one were to put their mind to it.  A Very Old Genus would probably be like that; Alien to most of us. 

Le Bella Pelligrina from the story was actually suspected of planting her vines wherever she went; "spreading the Gospel of Le Vecchia," the pilgrim herself and the equivalent of Aradia. 
  
The Voynich Manuscript must contain Locations of her "pilgrimage"  and that means the locations of the vines themselves.
 
So, that is the condensed version of the "Gospel" that may be coded within the Voynich Manuscript.  And by the way has anyone tried listening the the manuscript with the little headphone icon, it reads it to you.  Its hilarious.  My program gave it a hash tag and a few hundred Carats.     </reviewbody>
    <stars>5</stars>
    <reviewer>handkerchief976</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2024-08-01 02:06:15</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2024-08-01 02:06:15</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@handkerchief976</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <review>
    <reviewtitle>VOYNICH MANUSCRIPT translation -1</reviewtitle>
    <reviewbody>Dear Enthusiasts 

You may find the valid translation work on the Voynich Manuscript in the web page given below.
www.turkicresearch.com . This accurate study has been done by Mr. Ahmet Ardic and the ATA Team
and the detailed information you may find therein. The decipherment of any sort is not required as it seems basically but rather a translation (interpretation) of the north( north east) Khazarian Turkic language of the medieval ages may be required understandably. The north Black sea, Crimea and/or north Khazarian sea, possibly southern Urallic regions are where the infamous Golden Horde khanate lived and resided with a fine heritage of golden artifacts and other archeological items are present.
Other possible canditates of the major Turkic khanates may be the Crimean Khanate, or Cuman's, Kipcak's, Chatai's(?) from which the manuscript might have been ordered to be scribed. 
for more info:   fatihbodur.izmir@gmail.com </reviewbody>
    <stars>0</stars>
    <reviewer>Fatih Bodur</reviewer>
    <reviewdate>2025-06-03 11:56:29</reviewdate>
    <createdate>2025-06-03 11:52:36</createdate>
    <reviewer_itemname>@fatih_bodur</reviewer_itemname>
  </review>
  <info>
    <num_reviews>108</num_reviews>
    <avg_rating>4.52</avg_rating>
  </info>
</reviews>
